# EMILIO BERTI



(+45) 266 54 662 ♦ emilio.berti.academia@gmail.com

## **SUMMARY**

I am a theoretical ecologist with a passion for math and computing. I have an strong quantitative background, with expertise in mathematical and statistical modelling of complex systems using big databases at large spatio-temporal scales. I have worked in many different fields of biology, from the microscopic scale of muscle physiology to the global scale of vertebrates macroecology. I enjoy programming very much; I started by prototyping robots and I haven't stop since. I have achieved outstanding programming skills in several programming languages, particularly in R, python, and C++. I have a strong background in using Geographic Information Systems (GIS), especially in optimizing large computations or performing complex data analyses.

## WORK HISTORY

## PostDoctoral researcher

October 2020 - Present

Theory in Biodiversity Science

German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (IDIV)

Leipzig, Germany

#### Scientific consultant

May 2020 - July 2020

Department of Bioscience

Aarhus University

Aarhus, Denmark

## Teaching assistant

February 2017 - April 2020

Department of Biology Aarhus University

Aarhus, Denmark

### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD

February 2017 - June 2020

Section of Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

Department of Biology

Aarhus University

Aarhus, Denmark

# Visiting PhD student

Fall 2018

Department of Ecology and Evolution

University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

# MSc in Biology

2013 - 2016

Department of Ecology and Evolution

BSc in Biology 2009 - 2012

Department of Physiology University of Florence Florence, Italy

## POSTGRADUATE COURSES

"Species Distributions Modelling"	2019
Evora, Portugal – Lecturers: Prof. Miguel Araújo and Dr. Babak Naimi	
"Megafauna ecology – shaping past, present and future ecosystems."	2019
Aarhus, Denmark	
"Mixed models"	2019
Aarhus, Denmark – Lecturer: Prof. Rodrigo Labouriau	
"Writing and Speaking Science in English for Biology Students"	2019
Aarhus, Denmark – Lecturer: Prof. Brian Sorrell	
"Ecosystem roles of megafauna in the past, present, and future"	2017
Aarhus, Denmark	
"Mediterranean School of Complex Networks (MSCx)"	2017
Salina. Italy	

#### **SKILLS**

# Language

Italian (native), English (fluent), Danish (beginner)

#### **Programming**

R (expert), bash (expert), python (proficient), C/C++ (proficient), javascript (mostly for Google Earth Engine, beginner), julia (beginner), SQL (postgres falvor, proficient), html (beginner)

#### Software

Linux/GNU, Rstudio, Anaconda, Jupyter, QGIS, LATEX, Markdown, Pandoc, Git, GitHub, Overleaf Methods

Statistics, regression analysis, effect sizes, mixed models, variables selection, PCA, ordination and classification, optimization, machine learning, network analysis, mathematical modelling, extrapolation and forecasting, species distribution models, environmental niche modeling, spatial modeling, geographic information systems (GIS), demographic projections, quantitative genetic, big data, data visualization, data science, APIs, automation.

#### TEACHING & ORGANIZED WORKSHOPS

#### **Teaching**

Introduction to git and GitHub for a fool-proof programming (2022) – course

Introduction to scientific programming and tidyverse (2022) – slides

# Teaching Assistant

Meta-analyses for Biodiversity (2021)

Statistical and Geospatial Modelling (2019)

Behavioural Biology (2018, 2019)

Geographic Information System (2017)

# Organized Workshops

"Cleaning online repository data for use in biogeography and macroecology" (2019)

"Running a species distribution model in R." (2019)

"A (very) gentle introduction to Linux." (2019)

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Bauer, B., **Berti, E.**, ... & Brose, U. (2022). Biotic filtering by species' interactions constrains food-web variability across spatial and abiotic gradients. *Ecology letters*. DOI: 10.1111/ele.13995. (Shared first authorship).

Grenié, M, **Berti, E.**, ... & Marten, W. (2022). Harmonizing taxon names in biodiversity data: a review of tools, databases, and best practices. *Methods in Ecology and Evolution*. DOI: 10.1111/2041-210X.13802.

**Berti, E.**, Davoli, M., ... & Vollrath, F. (2021). The r package enerscape: A general energy landscape framework for terrestrial movement ecology. *Methods in Ecology and Evolution*. DOI: 10.1111/2041-210X.13734.

Berti, E., Monsarrat, S., Munk, M., Jarvie, S. & Svenning, J.C. (2020). Body size is a good proxy for vertebrate charisma. *Biological Conservation*. DOI: 10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108790.

**Berti, E.** & Svenning, J.C. (2020). Megafauna extinctions have reduced biotic connectivity worldwide. *Global Ecology and Biogeography*. DOI: 10.1111/geb.13182.

# PEER REVIEW

As of July 2022, I have done five peer reviews for: Ecography (2), Ecology Letters (2) and GigaScience (1). You can find more at my Publons profile.

#### LINKS

- Google Scholar profile
- Personal website
- ORCiD

- LinkedIn
- GitHub
- Publons